Guide to the Stanley J. Morrow stereographs 1861-1881
Montana Historical Society
Stanley J. Morrow Stereographs
1868-1881
Montana Historical Society Photograph Archives
ST 003
Morrow, Stanley J.
72 stereographs
Stanley J. Morrow was a prominent photographer in the Dakota and Montana territories who operated from 1868 through 1882. This collection of seventy stereographs contains scenes photographed by Morrow between 1868 and 1881. It includes views of Morrow’s home and studio in Yankton, D.T., military expeditions including views of General Crook’s 1876 expedition against the Lakota Sioux and images of George K. Sanderson’s cleanup of Little Bighorn Battlefield (1879), views of Fort Keogh (ca. 1878), and Indian portraits and village scenes.
Stanley J. Morrow was born in Richland County, Ohio, on May 3, 1843, and moved to Wisconsin early in his childhood. In 1861, he joined the 7th Wisconsin Volunteer Infantry as a drummer. Morrow was then transferred into the Veteran Reserve and was stationed at Point Lookout Prison in Maryland as an assistant to renowned Civil War photographer Matthew B. Brady. Brady instructed Morrow in photography and the wet plate process, which Morrow used throughout his career.
Upon exiting the war, Morrow married Isa Ketchum, and the couple moved to Yankton, Dakota, around 1868. Morrow established a photography gallery there and taught Isa the photographic process. When Morrow was away, Isa ran the gallery to fund his photographic expeditions.
In 1876, Stanley Morrow met soldiers returning from General George A. Crook’s expedition in pursuit of the Lakota Sioux and Cheyenne. Morrow photographed soldiers reenacting scenes from the starvation march back to the Black Hills and from the Battle of Slim Buttes, and photographed Sioux warriors captured in battle. Morrow became post photographer at Fort Keogh in 1878 and later that year opened a gallery at Fort Custer. In April 1879, while working as photographer at Fort Custer, he accompanied Captain George K. Sanderson and a company of the 11th Infantry on an expedition to Little Bighorn Battlefield to clear the field of animal bones and remark the graves of fallen soldiers.
Stanley Morrow returned to Yankton in 1880, photographing local events including the Great Flood of 1881.When Isa fell ill in 1882, the couple moved to Florida. Stanley J. Morrow died in Dallas, Texas, on December 10, 1921.
This collection of seventy stereographs contains scenes in the Dakota and Montana territories captured by Morrow between 1868 and 1881. It includes images of the Little Bighorn Battlefield including the marking of graves (1879); Crow, Cheyenne, Sioux, and Gros Ventre villages and portraits of individuals; views of soldiers returned from General Crook’s expedition, including a soldier re-enacting shooting a horse for food and captured Sioux Indians (1876); the Morrow family, home and studio in Yankton, D.T., and steamboats (including the Helena) and an ice gorge from the Great Flood of 1881; officers quarters and troops at Ft. Keogh; the Gates of the Mountains, Prickly Pear Canyon, and other scenes in the vicinity of Helena, Montana.
The stereographs are arranged into six series: Series I. Custer’s Battlefield, Series II. Indian Series, Series III. Crook’s Expedition Against Sitting Bull 1876, Series IV. Miscellaneous, Series V. Local Series, Yankton, and Series VI. General. The first five series are Morrow’s series titles, but include some stereographs on the same subjects which are not included in Morrow’s series lists. Series VI. General contains images with no series labels that do not fall under any previous series. This series contains two subseries: Subseries I. Military and Subseries II. Other. The series are all ordered by the original stereograph numbers, when possible, both at the series level and within each series. Each item description includes the item ID, the original stereograph number and title assigned by Morrow, any additional descriptive title in brackets, and the title of the set in which the stereograph was issued.
Collection is open for research.
The bulk of the stereographs were transferred from the MHS Museum (1939 donation); the collection also contains stereographs from the following accessions: Mrs. H. H. Mitten donation (1958), PAc 86-34, PAc 89-44, and PAc 2006-26.
Spreadsheet list available in Photograph Archives reference room.
This collection is indexed under the following headings. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
United States -- Army
Cheyenne Indians; Dakota Indians; Crow Indians; Indians of North America; Steamboats -- South Dakota -- Yankton
Yankton (S.D.); Fort Keogh (Mont.); Little Bighorn Battlefield (Mont.)
Stereographs
Montana; Native Americans; Military
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Custer's Battlefield, Series I
  Morrow issued two sets of stereographs with the same views under this series. One set was numbered 34-44 in the set “Photographic Views of the Great Northwest,” and these were later renumbered 185-196 to be incorporated into the set “Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest.”
  - No. 34 “Gen'l Custer's last stand, looking in direction of ford and Indian village.”, (Pile of bones in foreground with river in distance; same image as 010); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 01
  - No. 35 “Custer's battle field. Lettering the head-boards.”, (Soldier with paint brush lettering headboard of Lieut. J. J. Crittenden, 20th Infantry); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 02
  - No. 36 “Supposed grave of Lieut. Sturgis.”, (Wooden sign nailed on stick. Sign lettering reads: "Lt. Sturgis, 7th Cav, June 25, 76); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 03
  - No. 37 “Bluff on the Little Horn, where some of Custer's men were driven to a watery grave.”, (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 04
  - No. 38 “Decorating the graves on Custer's Battle field.”, (Capt. George K. Sandernson, standing; Sign on headstone reads: "Col. Keogh and 8 Soldiers of Co. 17 Cav. Killed Here June 25, 1876"; Corp. John Wild's headboard is behind Keogh marker; same image as 006); (Views of Gen'l Crook's Expedition and the Black Hills); 1879; 05
  - No. 38 “Decorating the graves on Custer's Battle field.”, (Capt. George K. Sandernson, standing; Sign on headstone reads: "Col. Keogh and 8 Soldiers of Co. 17 Cav. Killed Here June 25, 1876"; Corp. John Wild's headboard is behind Keogh marker; same image as 005); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 06
  - No. 39 “Unknown, showing several graves and the ridge where the last stand was made.”, (Wooden sign nailed on stick. Sign lettering reads: Unknown; same image as 011); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 07
  - No. 40 “Bones gathered on the Custer's hill previous to placing them in the monument.”, (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 08
  - No. 44 “The ford, where Custer attempted to cross to attack the Indian village.”, (Little Bighorn River); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 1879; 09
  - No. 185, 34 “Gen'l Custer's last stand, looking in direction of ford and Indian village.”, (The place where Gen. Custer's body was found and buried by soldiers and again by Gen. Crooks men; same image as 001); (Photographic Gems of the Great North-West); 1879; 10
  - No. 190 “Bones and unknown graves.”, (Wooden sign nailed on stick. Sign lettering reads: Unknown; same image as 007); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1879; 11
- Indian Series, Series II
  Morrow’s Indian Series list includes 83 titles, 19 of which are represented in this collection along with three without series labels, and three unmarked stereographs.
  - No. 23 “Village of the Cheyenne Prisoners near Fort Keogh, M.T. 1878.”, (Group of tepees); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 12
  - No. 101 “Pretty Horse, daughter of White Bull, chief of the Sans Arc (Sioux).”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 13
  - No. 109 “Sioux Graves 1870.”, "Sioux graves - buried on poles." "This photo was in Montana and while Mr. Morrow was taking the pictures he was shot at by an Indian that objected to his taking the photo. Mr. Morrow was a good runner and the Indian a poor shot. This spot was about a mile from the river where the "Boat" was taking on wood. The captain of the boat advised Mr. Morrow to not go for the photo; but he went anyhow and nearly lost his life. Mr. Morrow never went armed, he spoke the Sioux language very good."; (Photographic Gems from the Great North-West); 14
  - No. 112 “1877 Scene on Ponca Creek, Indians boating.”, (Photographic Gems from the Great North-West); 15
  - No. 116 “Unc-pa-pa Squaw, Sioux Nation 1877. ”, (Studio portrait of Indian woman); (Photographic Gems from the Great North-West); 16
  - No. 123 “Red River carts made without iron. Tires of raw hide.”, (Group of Indians, one standing and the rest seated on the tongues of wagons); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 17
  - No. 124, 24 “Bull Boat - Made of Buffalo Hide 1877.”, (Photographic Gems from the Great North-West); 18
  - No. 128 “Issuing annuities to the Three Nations, Fort Berthold, Dakota.”, (Large groups of Indian people seated in circles); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 19
  - No. 130 “Gros Ventres Medicine Lodge, Fort Berthold - dirt lodge.”, (Hidatsa); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 20
  - No. 131 “Spotted Tail (Sin-te-ga-lis-kai) Chief of the Brule Sioux with his favorite wife and daughter.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 21
  - No. 134 “Two Strike, 2d chief of the Brule Sioux.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 22
  - No. 136 “Yellowstone Kelly, setting traps for beaver.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 23
  - No. 137 “Indian discovers Kelly's trail.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 24
  - No. 141 “Assinaboine Sioux Village at the mouth of the Yellowstone.”, (Cloth tepee in foreground, Indian women and child nearby in front of other tepees); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 25
  - No. 148 “Indian village Fort Berthold D.T. (Dakota Territory) looking North.”, (Arickaree Village - Dirt Lodges - Fort Berthold, D.T. (title from Indian Series)); 26
  - No. 151 “Sisseton Squaws - Sioux- Fort Totten D.T. (Dakota Territory).”, (Portrait of two seated Indian women); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 27
  - No. 157 “Bannock Prisoners captured by Gen (Nelson A.) Miles, 1879.”, (Group of Indian men posed in front of a tall board fence); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 28
  - No. 164, 165, 12 “Cheyenne village. Drying Buffalo meat and hides.”, (Cheyenne Village on the Yellowstone. (title from the Indian Series)); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 29
  - No. 171, 21 “Crow squaw, dress trimmed with Elk teeth.”, (Indian woman standing, holding a blanket); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 30
  - No. 175, 9 “Sioux warriors, (Titon) (Teton), in council costume and war bonnets.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 31
  - No. 178, 180 “Crow Squaw, summer costume nude to the waist.”, (Indian woman posed); (Views of the Great Flood at Yankton, D.T., 1881.); 32
  - No. 182 “Crow Squaw in summer costume.”, (Indian woman posed nude to the waist with a buffalo robe over her shoulders); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 33
  - No. (15), (Indian women dressing buffalo hides and showing manner of stretching them; Cheyenne village on the Yellowstone River; 1869-70 series); 1869-1870; 34
  - (Large teepee, possibly Cheyenne, with animal skins lying across the cover.), 1869-1870; 35
  - (Portrait of two Indian men seated in front of cloth backdrop. They are holding repeating rifles.), (Photographic Gems from the Great North-West); 36
  - No. (24) "Iron Bull, chief of the Crow Nation.", (Indian man posed); (Photographic Views from the Great North-West); 72
- Crook's Expedition Against Sitting Bull, Series III
  Morrow photographed 31 images for this formal series, and this collection consists of seven of those stereographs. Two stereographs in this series were part of Morrow’s original set on Crook’s expedition, numbered 1-31. Nineteen of the photographs in that set were later renumbered 197-215 and incorporated into Morrow’s “Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest” set.
  - No. 11 “Bear Rock, from the north, showing Bears Head.”, (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1876; 37
  - No. 12 “Gen. Merritt and Officers of the Fifth Cavalry.”, (Groups of soldiers seated on rocks: 2nd Lt. Charles D. Parkhust, Lt. William C. Hunter, Kellogg or Riley, 1st Lt. Alfred B. Bache, Major Julius W. Mason, Col. Wesley Merritt, Captain Emil Adam, 2nd Lt. Satterlee C. Plummer, 2nd Lt. Hoel S. Bishop, 2nd Lt. Robert London, 1st Lt. Charles King, 1st Lt. William P. Hall, Major John J. Upham, A.A.S. Junius L. Powell, Captain Edward H. Lieb, Captain John S. Payne, Captain Calbraith P. Rogers, Captain Edward M. Hayes, Captain Albert E. Woodson, 2nd Lt. Edward L. Keyes, 2nd Lt. Julius H. Pardee, 1st Lt. William C. Forbush, Captain Robert H. Montgomery, Captain George F. Price); (Views of the Great Flood at Yankton, D.T., 1881.); 1876; 38
  - No. 200 “Supply train camped near Custer City, Black Hills.”, (Covered wagons in a circle, men standing by the wagons); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1876; 39
  - No. 202 “Sioux captured at the Battle of Slim Buttes.”, (Group of Indians, mainly women and young children wearing blankets; Charging Bear standing at left); (Crook's Expedition Against Sitting Bull 1876); 40
  - No. 208 “Corral formed by packs for the pack train.”, (Chief Packer Tom Moore seated between two of his men); (Views of the Great Flood at Yankton, D.T., 1881); 1876; 41
  - No. 210 “Soldiers shooting abandoned horse for food.”, (Reenactment of the time that Gen. Crook's men had to shoot their horses for food); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1876; 42
  - No. 214 “Army in camp at Point of Rocks Buffalo Gap.”, (Tents and wagons at base of rock formation); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1876; 43
- Miscellaneous, Series IV
  Stereographs in this series were issued in the set “Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest.” Morrow lists 48 stereographs in his Miscellaneous series, numbered 268-315. This collection includes nine stereographs from his list.
  - No. 268 “Going through Prickly Pear Canon Rocky Mts.”, (Horse-drawn wagon in the distance on a dirt road in the canyon); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1870; 44
  - No. 268 “Mrs. Isa Morrow and daughter, Nellie, in the rear, Mr. Morrow in front wagon going from Fort Benton to Helena, Montana, Rocky Mountains - 1870.”, (Carriage and covered wagon on a dirt road in Prickly Pear Canyon); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 45
  - No. 270 “Pulpit rock, Prickly Pear Canon Rocky Mts.”, 1870; 46
  - No. 273 “Silver Rapids, Prickly Pear Canon Rocky Mts.”, 1870; 47
  - No. 277 “The soldier's pet, Grisley (Grizzly) Bear.”, (Soldier holding a seated bear); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 48
  - No. 280 “Fort Benton, Montana.”, (Looking up the street lined with buildings. Signs on buildings read: Overland Hotel and Carroll Steell. Same image as 050); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1871; 49
  - No. 280 “Fort Benton - 1871.”, (same image as 049); 50
  - No. 282 “Missouri River Steamer at Fort Benton.”, "Ida Reese sunk at mo.(mouth) of White River, June 20, 1871. Levee, Fort Benton 1871"; 51
  - No. 283 “Ranche on Teton River near Fort Benton.”, (The Old "Stocking Ranch". View from a distance of corrals and a circle of log buildings located next to a river.); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 52
  - No. 356 “Heart Arch, Fort Keogh in a distance.”, (Rock formation.); 53
- Local Series, Yankton, Series V
  Morrow lists 22 stereographs in his series, Local Series, Yankton. One of the listed stereographs is included in this series along with five other views of Yankton.
  - No. 316 “View of the ice gorge at the ways, looking east.”, (Steamboats on river surrounded by ice. Yankton, D.T.); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1881; 54
  - No. 317 “View of the steamers on the ways.”, (Block P steamboats on river surrounded by ice. Yankton, D.T.); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1881; 55
  - No. 330 “Steamer Helena after the heavy rise April 5th. Elevator and depot in distance.”, (Steamboat Helena on river surrounded by ice. Yankton, D.T.); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 1881; 56
  - No. 368 “3rd St from Walnut; southside looking east.”, "Yankton Dakota -1868. This was the studio and home of Mr. Morrow from 1867 to 1870 and studio only 1867-1882."; (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 57
  - No. 377 “View on 3d street looking west from Walnut. 1881.”, (Two women looking at sign for Morrow Views in front of Morrow's studio.); (Photographic Gems of the Great Northwest); 58
  - “Mrs. Isa A. Morrow Yankton Dakota 1869.”, "Mrs. Morrow was a photographer, she learned the business from her husband in 1866 and when Mr. Morrow was on his trips she ran The Photograph Gallery, which helped finance his trips. She quit the work in 1882. She died at the age of 82 at Santa Ana, Calif."; (Photographic Gems Among the Wild Indians of Dakota.); 59
- General, Series VI
  This series comprises stereographs that do not fall under the previous series. The first subseries primarily consists primarily consists of stereographs that Morrow captured as post photographer at Ft. Keogh. The second subseries includes all other views, many taken in the Helena, Montana, area.
  - Military, Subseries A
    - No. 23 “Company of the Fifth U.S. Infantry in Camp in Montana 1878.”, (Soldiers form a line in front of their Sibley tents); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); 60
    - No. 119 “One of the Montana Forts - name unknown. 1868 or 1869. ”, (View of sky full of clouds, roofs of log buildings in foreground.); (Photographic Gems from the Great Northwest); 61
    - “Group of Officers Children & qrs.(quarters), at Fort Keogh M.T.”, (Group of women and children sitting in front of the officers' quarters); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); circa 1878; 62
    - “Fort Keogh, MT.”, (View of the fort in the distance); (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); circa 1878; 63
    - “Row of Officers Quarters at Fort Keogh M.T.”, (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); circa 1878; 64
    - “Officers Quarters Fort Keogh M.T.”, (Photographic Views of the Great North-West); circa 1878; 65
  - Other, Subseries B
    - No. 203 “Scene below the Gates of the Mountains. Missouri Riv. (River)”, (Photographic Gems from the Great Northwest); 66
    - No. 205 “Scene below the Gates of the Mts, Missouri Riv. (River)”, (Photographic Gems from the Great Northwest); 67
    - "Water Flume Upper and Helena City in the early 70s." (Flume possibly at the south end of Main Street, Helena, Montana, used for mining.), (Photographic Gems from the Great Northwest); 68
    - “Entrance to Silver Mine, Montana.”, (Man with shovel standing near mine entrance with ore car on track); (Views of the Great Flood at Yankton, D.T., 1881.); 69
    - “Carriage Road to Ft. Totton - 1870.”, (Mrs. Morrow and daughter Nellie (in distance) - on rocks near the water.); 70
- Crooks Expedition and the Black Hills, Series VII
  Morrow includes two classes in his series Crook’s Expedition and the Black Hills. Class 1 contains 31 stereographs, and this collection consists of one of these stereographs. Class 2 contains eight stereographs.
  - Class 1, No. 27 "Buckskin Lodge, Sioux prisoners, Gen. Custer's battle flag captured at the Battle of Slim Buttes, and the officers in command of the charge."; (Oglala Lakota and possibly Cheyenne prisoners from the Battle of Slim Buttes in front of a teepee.); 1876; 71